Hello everyone this is the third and final module of the diagnosis lesson. As you've seen
the lesson has been divided in three modules. Module one that was about an introduction about
all diagnosis and already in the first module the ISO 1429 alias UDS has been mentioned.
The module two that was more focused about the status rights and how to get to the specific
status and how to get back from that status still using the concepts behind this norm. Finally
this last and shorter module will have a look at the norm itself so as you see here this is the
ISO that has been always mentioned the ISO 14229 and here you find also the meaning of the acronym
Unified Diagnostic Service UDS. Since it is mentioned so many times in the lessons and also in your
daily working activities I would like to show and scroll down with you the norm to show what we
really care about this norm and how to use it. So as every norm there is a summary of contents
there are a lot of reference or references terms and definitions symbols so a lot of
introductory pages and chapters where you know everything that is will be used during the norm
is explained. But what we really care about is okay it would be interesting to read the first part
you know we're talking about like 30-35 pages so it would be interesting to read also the first pages
as well but once you are aware and you have basic knowledge about the UDS you will use this norm just
looking at the services that you might need for your activities. As you see here
there is a huge list of services all the services that are expected for this norm. So you see here the
service 10 service 11 which we probably mentioned the service 27 here 22 and stuff like this. As you see the
list of services is quite long and here you find also the service 14 that was mentioned in module 2 as well
as the service 19 which is the main one that is mentioned and used almost in all the modules about the
diagnosis that we have done before until now. Service 19 is the biggest one with the largest amount of
sub-services probably for the activities we are interested in so the description of the norm will start from
the easiest of the services that you will probably find yourself using which is the service 22. So just
looking at the summary of the contents we just have to find the service 22 with data by identifier service 22
that is page 97. So here we basically go to the page and we see how a specific service is
set. This kind of structure is repeated for every service. So we are going to see the service 22 but then
this kind of structure is repeated for every service. As mentioned many times in the past as well
you don't have to remember everything by hearth. I mean no one will ask you to remember the whole norm
or the whole norm in every service in every subservice no one will ask you for that. What you have
what you have to remember what you have to to have basically is the norm itself so once you start an
activity if you have to perform some activities about the diagnosis what you will need is basically
diagnostic requirements for that project and if for that project the UDS is used then all you need to
have to have is the UDS itself. So once you have to do an activity I don't know reading an information
reading the error memo raising the error memory whatever you know that you can look in the ISO 14229
alias UDS and then look for the you know the service that you might need how to write it what you should
expect and things like this. So even if there are 300 pages do not get scared because what is really
useful and helpful here is to have the norm read it through and knowing that you can look for
information that you need just reading the norm every time you need it. We will start from service
22 because it is very easy and then we will move to the service 19 which is the main one that we have
always mentioned in use in the previous lessons. As always there is the service description and this is
very helpful because if you already know the service to be used and you just don't remember how to write
it in a frame okay then you can jump this this part this section but if you don't know what is the
service that you might need then the service description of all the services might be helpful for you because
it can explain what can you do with this service and eventually reading through them you can find something
that can be that can suit the suit the activities that you might do so you can find the service that
you might need reading the service description. In this case we already know what this service is used for
but in case you have doubts you can simply read the service description to have a first introduction of
the service in itself. I suggest you to do this kind of like to read at least the service description for the
main services that have been mentioned in the diagnostic lessons that you might have received.
After the description there's always the request message definition so in the norm you will find the
long list of a long a huge number of tables okay so it's important to understand how to read them. In this
case you will always have a chapter of request message as you remember all the diagnostic services are sent to
the electronic control units using diagnostic scan frames okay so what you see here this is actually
the hexadecimal values that you should write inside the scan frame to send diagnostic request. In this table
in fact you see that on the left side there is data byte so the amount of bytes that are needed for this
request and here what is the parameter name and there is the hexadecimal values. Then reading the norm you can
understand also what is this CVT or this mnemonic section but for all we need now what is important
is just to focus on the first column of the data byte eventually the parameter name and hexadecimal. So from
here we see that to write to use the request this service the service 22 we have to write the request message in this way
so we have a first byte where we have the read data by identifier request service id which is the id of
the service the id of the service is 22 we already mentioned it so it means that if i want to request this
kind of a service the message should start with 22 okay then it's said that the the second section of the data
byte is byte 2 and byte 3 and byte 2 and byte 3 there is the data identifier so actually the code of the RDI
okay this is always defined in two bytes so it means that if you want to read a specific information
you will write 22 and the two bytes of the RDI okay as you see the table doesn't stop here because one of
the feature of you know one of the possibilities that you have with this service is to request
more than one RDI per times this is not always possible but it might be possible so this is why
the table doesn't stop here and it means that you can send 22 then the two bytes for the first RDI
other two bytes for the second one until you know all the RDIs that you want to all
uh request for okay we can use the basic example of requesting just one uh uh RDI so what we will have
is 22 and there two bytes at 10 0 8 for example okay where this will be the RDI and this is the service okay
so this is the request then let's move on uh i choose this service because this service does not consider
sub function but uh i'm reading the chapter 19 you will see that the chapter sorry the chapter related
to service 19 you will see that this chapter will be much much longer because the service in itself
expects a lot of sub functions we have mentioned the 1902 the 1904 the 1906 and the slides you will find
many others much more of that but in this specific service there are no sub function so it's very it's
easier for the explanation uh but uh going through the service 19 you will see that this chapter will be
actually much more longer than this one where it's simply written this service does not use a sub function
parameter so here it's explained what is the data identifier and what this parameter identifies the
service data record being requested by the client and here there are also other references inside norm to
understand what is this data identifier and how and why it's built like that
so there is not just the table explaining uh uh how to write the request but also what is the positive
response message definition that i should expect once i sent these i sent this uh request okay this service
so again i wrote and before 22 10 0 8 then here the norm says okay this is the answer okay and here it's
described the answer so the answer will be 62 because as you know as you might already know or
someone has mentioned already in other videos the positive response to a specific service is going to
be plus 40 in hexadecimal values so if we requested service 22 then the positive response will always start
with plus 40 on the service so if you requested the service 22 then the positive response will be 22
plus 40 in hexadecimal which is going to be 62 and here everything is described here i mean positive
response message that message definition quite likely quite likely inside the first chapter descriptive
chapters of the norm you will also also find a description of this plus 40 when there is a positive
response and stuff like that uh in these tables this concept is given for granted but we are already
mentioning that once we have a positive response it's going to be a plus 40. anyway so we have a plus 40
then here it's data identifier so we will have 10 0 8 because this is that identifier and then we will
have the data record so the actual information so if we are considering that this byte uh this byte i don't know here
the content of the byte definition so that the rdi is on two bytes okay so 10 0 8 okay but then the content
that it gives access to it gives access to might be i don't know 10 bytes okay so here we will have 62 as a positive
response 10 0 8 which is the id data identifier and then we will have 10 bytes giving us the content of
this rdi just remember back guys that rdi basically is an information that is stored inside the electronic
control unit memory so what i'm doing basically here requesting the service 22 is just requesting to the
electronic control unit uh this information to give and publish this information on the ken network
using this specific syntax coming from vds uh then if the rdi it's uh it's just i don't know it has two bytes
of information then we will just have this one one and two if it's on three bytes we have always this
or if it's on four bytes we have this one as well and stuff like this okay this should be quite clear
and this is explained inside the norm so in the norm is said okay the positive response message
definition is going to be like this so i have one as 62 the positive response the identification codes
of the data identifier and the content once again the table doesn't stop here because as i explained you
before you have the chance to request more than one rdi times this is not always possible it's up also to
the client that how the client decides to uh implement this part this section maybe they don't want to
implement exactly the uds but maybe they have some division in the software so not always is possible
to request more than one rdi times but the norm says that it's possible to read a few of them all
together okay this is why the table doesn't stop but the idea is always the same so you have 62 the two bytes of
the identifier and the content once the content is finished you will have once again data identifier
and the content okay this should be clear here there is a definition of what is the data identifier
and the data record but once again data identifier this is basically the identification number the data
record is the content we access through that identifier once again guys here we are just uh this service is very
easy so through the service 22 we are requesting to read some information that are stored inside the uh
memory of the electronic content this information is stored with the specific identification number which we
um consider to be 1008 we request can you give me the information that are uh stored with the
identification number 1008 the echo will reply okay 62 1008 blah blah blah blah this is the content okay
this should be quite easy then uh let's move to the next section of the norm which is the supported
negative responses so every time we in this example we have given for granted that the positive that the
response is positive and we explain that once we have the positive response is always plus 40 on the
service that has been requested but for some reasons the echo can also reply saying i cannot give you this
information so we request 22 i'll use purple so we always request the service in this way because you
know we have seen it from but we have two options or deposit the response is positive and it follows the rules that
we were explaining before or we have the second options where the answer is negative so the echo cannot reply
to cannot you know reply positively to the services that we requested so in this case the structure will be like
this one the first byte is always going to be 7f so the answer is going to be 7f 7f is used every time
the echo wants to tell us the echo wants to tell us okay this is a negative response negative response to
what second byte is going to be the service for which the response is negative and the service that we
were requesting is the service 22 this is the second byte the third byte is going to be the the reason
so the the echo always when there is a negative response the echo will always reply on these three bytes
where the first one is the 7f always which tells okay every time you read 7f as first byte this is a
negative response so negative response means i cannot reply okay i cannot reply to what the service 22 and
then the echo always tells you why so in this case the third byte is the reason of why that the echo cannot reply
uh in the norm there should be a table with all the possible negative responses that the uds expects
but not all the negative responses are expected for every service so for every service that you read there
is also a section of supported negative responses and there is a subtable containing only the
a supported negative responses for that service so it means that if i use the service 22 the i have two
options or the echo replies positive positively and that's that follows all the words that we have explained
before but the other option is that the answer is negative and we will have 7f 22 and one of these negative
responses so we will have these are the ones supported for the service 22 so we will have the service the
reason 13 incorrect message length or invalid format means that we have requested an rdi not on two bytes but
you know to buy it point something so we didn't write 22 10 0 8 but we brought 22 10 0 8 1 for example
and this is wrong because the rdi are based on two bytes okay so this is the reason why we have the
correct uh incorrect message length another negative response could be 22 so 7f 22 22 conditions not
correct it means that you are requesting a diagnostic request when there are not all the proper conditions
and expected conditions to request this service 31 request out of range so you requested an rdi that
doesn't exist for example or security access denied 33 so you are requesting a diagnostic service that cannot
be requested with this security access level the security access there is also a diagnostic service for
the security access which is the 27 so you can have a look at it read it to understand what is this security
access once again the structure that we are seeing here for the service 22 is all is the same for the
service 27 the service 19 the service 14 and stuff like this okay so it's okay and it's enough to go
through the structure of one service because all the others follow the same structure
and then the the norm also gives us some examples so there are some preconditions that are explained
here these are these are all the preconditions of this example and then there is an example probably there
are also also more than one example so this example one is read single data identifier so we just are
reading one rdi this guy's in this case is the bin vehicle so the vehicle identification number bin number
so we will we will actually write inside the diagnostic tool or simply in a diagnostic frame in canalizer
these three bytes 22 because this is the proper diagnostic service and then we will have the two bytes of the
the identification number which is the f19 in this case okay so the echo will reply again uh the positive
response 62 then the two bytes with the data identifier and the content of that ed of that rdi in this case
the content of that rdi is based on uh 20 minus 3 17 bytes so the answer will be on 20 bytes because the first is
the positive response then we will have the two bytes of the rdi and finally the content of the rdi
uh here there is another example where you read not just one rdi but two rdi's so as you can see
this reflects exactly what was written in the generic uh variables let's say in the table before you just
write the service 22 and then two bytes for the first rdi two bytes for the second rdi and the answer
in this case will be 72 because it's positive response the first the two bytes of the first rdi
the content the two bytes of the second rdi and the content and it ends so here it starts another
service another service another service that will follow the same structure so out of curiosity because
we have always used that service we are going to scroll down also the service 19 service 19
uh service 19 so we see there is a productive part where it's written uh for which are the reasons
why we should use this service which is the purpose of this service and we see here also the descriptive
part is descriptive part descriptive part is much longer because there is a huge set of sub services
that are used for service 19. this is very helpful so i really uh invite you to read these chapters
especially for the main services that services that you might use for your activities so there is always
the descriptive part as you see it's very very long uh you know there are even different
chapters to understand which are the service which is the services which are the purposes of the
sub services and stuff like this okay so this is very very long but this is these are all the concepts
as ideas that we gave you in the past videos so just reading through these sections you should find
every all the things that we have already mentioned in the past in other videos so once this full
introductive part has been defined probably there is also the definition of the status byte that you
have in other videos so you see how long is this then you will have the usual table that we already found
in the other services so there is the request message definition here you see there is first byte is the
service 19 the second byte is the sub function which was not present in the uh in the table before
because no sub services were expected for service 22 but for the service 19 there is a huge bunch of
sub services expected and then there is the third byte of the status mask this is the famous 19 0208 that
we have always mentioned in past videos okay but as you see there are 02 is just part of subs it is just one
of the all the sub services that are expected for this service so we have 0 1 0 2 0 half 11 12 12 13
0 3 0 4 0 5 0 6 10 you know there are there is a long long list of sub services each sub service is
used for a specific purpose most of the activities that we do can be managed just with the the subservice
0 2 sub services 0 4 and the subservice is 0 6 but there are a bunch of other subservices that might be
helpful for other specific corner cases of your activity and you don't have to remember all of
them all you have to do is just knowing that i have the norm i can use the norm and read the chapter when
i need it to understand if there is a specific service or subservice that i can use to you know perform
a specific validation activity or verification activity that i'm supposed to do in my work
so here is the definition of all the sub function expected here you see the subservice 0 2 which is
the one that we always use is called report dtc by status mask so we say service 19 subservice 0 2
report the list of dtc by status mask which status mask at least 0 8 so at least the status all the dtc's
that has got at least the bit 3 to 1 this is the reason why we set 0 8 but this is the reason why we
can use whatever other status mask i'm not forced to use the 0 8 as the third byte of the request 19 0 2 0 8
i can use something different i don't know i'm interested in the list of the dtc's that have
third byte 40 so 19 0 2 40 or 19 0 2 f f 19 0 2 0 0 f and you can use it as you prefer according to the
activity that you want to do most of the time if we use 0 8 because we are interested in all the dtc's
that are at least saved in the error memory but this doesn't mean that you cannot use a different status mask
so this is the survey the list of all the subservices expected or that you that can be implemented for
service 19 just remember in the service 22 this section was empty because there are no subservices
expected for that service in this one you know you see there are also two or three pages so description
of the subservices okay so you start to understand why this is so important
so here there is the long definition of the status by the examples so i really invite you to read all of that
and once again as we have seen for the service 22 here there is a positive response message definition so what i should expect
what i should expect once i have a positive response once again if the service is the 19
then if there is the positive response it's going to be 19 plus 40 59 okay then 59 0 2 for example
the dtc status availability mask which i invite you to study and so this is the third byte that you
should study from the north and then the three bytes of the dtc because you know the dtc
uh is based on three bytes plus four byte real status of the dtc which we which is what we are looking for
and here there are all the examples of positive response with all the subservices so this chapter
is very long because we have a lot a lot of subservices it means we have a lot of tables for
every kind of example uh of course even here there is the supported negative responses code
in this case we have just three cases like some function not supported uh the incorrect message
length that we have always also seen on the service 22 and also the request out of range
and finally there is also the message for examples with what can be yeah here you see there is also the
description of what the what are the eight bit of the status byte and that's you know you have two
specific videos explaining that so this is just a refresh for you and then there are you know there
are examples where you know a specific uh subservice is used in this case is the one
the results i might say an example with zero two you know you see here in this case uh they're not
requesting the 1902 08 but they're interested in the more restrictive case where not just the bit 3 is
2 1 but in this case they want bit 7 1 and the bit uh 2 to 1 okay and you know here for it follows a
huge list of examples with all the subservices so just to uh sum it up this norm is not something that
you read so you take this norm you read 300 pages and then you expect to be expert in ugs no
this norm is very important to understand the structure of the norm probably start from service
22 because that's the easy one and once it's clear the structure of every service every time
you perform diagnostic activities use this norm uh looking for or the specific service if you don't
remember the syntax because we have seen there are tables explaining you how to write the request which
is the positive response to be expected which is the negative exponent response to be expected and also
which is the which are the negative reasons for the negative uh response expected so you just read the
norm if you don't remember the syntax or if you have to do something diagnostic diagnostic related but you don't
know which can be the service to be used you can simply or read the service description of all the
of all the services or simply just looking for keywords for example dtc for example flash of
uh echo for example arrays and stuff like this probably the research the control find feature of the laptop
uh applied on the norm will uh bring you to the service description chapter which is the first
section of every uh service and then once you read the service description that will help you to
understand if that can be a service that can help you for your validation activities or for your
verification activities or diagnosis and again you don't have to remember everything about the
service you just have to know how to read the UDS norm how to use it so that will help you for the
further activities that you do once again if there are doubts or problems you can contact me
uh i am pasquale.perrota and the email address is pasquale.perrota head sign kinethon.it or simply
refer to the generic mailing list automotive.training head sign kinethon.it for further uh support and further questions